Guide to the Eugene Marshall Papers, 1839-1962
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Education was a recurrent theme in Marshall's letters and papers. Most of this material was generated during his tenure as a schoolteacher in Massachusetts and Wisconsin in the 1850s and later as a parent and member of the school board of Caledonia, Minn., in the period after the Civil War, by the experience of his daughter, Anna, instructing in schools in Alabama, Mississippi, and Tennessee at the turn of the century, and by the career of his niece and her colleagues in Brockton, Mass., who lived in Olive (Marshall) Trow's boardinghouse. This material may be found under the following subject heads: education, teachers and teaching, and school facilities. Marshall himself held strong opinions on the proper education of children and women. He was reluctant to begin the teaching of children at home at an early age, and he was opposed to exposing women to a rigorous program of scholarship, which he thought would be ruinous to their health [letters, 1853-1857, 1870-1913]. Marshall himself demonstrated a lively curiosity on a great number of subjects and was not reluctant to attend lectures by visiting speakers. Among those whom he heard were Horace Mann, the educational reformer, and James Stanley Grimes, a theorist of phrenology, a subject which intrigued Marshall for a while thereafter [diary, 1851]. Marshall recorded some impressions of Union University at Murfreesboro, Tenn., where his regiment was billeted during the Civil War. There is also some material pertinent to the histories of two other southern universities. One of Marshall's sister's former boarders was Laura Gill, who had been dean of Barnard College and had been hired by the University of the South at Suwannee, Tenn., to set up a coordinate college for women there. Marshall's sister urged Eugene to visit her former boarder while both were in Tennessee. By the time Marshall had acted on his sister's suggestion, Miss Gill had left Suwannee for a similar assignment at Trinity College, Durham, N.C. [letters, 1908-1914]. Additional material pertaining to Laura Gill may be found in the Duke University Archives, Earl Waters Porter's A History of Trinity College and Duke, 1892-1924, and the B. N. Duke and Tillinghast Family MSS. in this library.
Among the locales described in the papers as a result of Marshall's extensive travelling are: Huntsville, Ala.; the Mississippi river front of Arkansas; Cairo, Ill.; Keokuk and and Sioux City, Io.; Calloway County and Smithland, Ky.; New Orleans, La.; Caledonia, St. Paul, and St. Peter, Minn.; Yankton, S.D.; Mansfield, Memphis, and Nashville, Tenn.; Galveston and San Antonio, Tex.; Fond du Lac, Milwaukee, and Ripon, Wisc.; and parts of Mississippi, Missouri, Montana, and Rhode Island. He also provides a few glimpses of life in Sheboygan, Wisc., and Clarksville, Tenn., the effects of the Civil War on Calloway County and Smithland, Ky., St. Louis, Mo., Carroll County, Mansfield, and Nashville, Tenn., and northern Alabama, and life in Minnesota during the Civil War and Sioux liars. Marshall also recorded some descriptive material on the territory of New Mexico which was recounted to him.
Of the various places described in the Marshall papers, none emerges as fully as does Brockton, Mass., through the letters [1861-1910] of Eugene's sister Olive. Olive (Marshall) Trow became the proprietor of a boardinghouse when her husband's health failed, and she remained in her hometown for the rest of her life, during which rural North Bridgewater, once a poor agricultural community of native New Englanders, became Brockton, a small but rapidly expanding manufacturing city with a diverse immigrant population. Olive's primary connection with these and other societal changes were her daughter Lizzie, a schoolteacher, and Lizzie's colleagues who boarded at the Trows'.
Olive was a nativist and betrayed a contempt for immigrants, who included Irish, Swedes, French Canadians, Italians, Jews, and blacks. She and her neighbors attempted to discriminate against new groups through real covenants which prohibited resale of property to specific nationalities [1899-1900]. She was troubled by greater militancy and expectations of Brockton's labor pool, particularly domestic servants. The city went through a difficult time in the winter following the coal miners' strike of 1902, and Olive expressed strong anti-union sentiments. She was displeased when Socialist candidates won positions in local government. Her letters also supply other economic indicators. She occasionally offered fairly general assessments of the state of the economy in Massachusetts, while other of her letters are rather specifically directed to the salaries, etc., of teachers in the local area. On a related note, Olive was considerably more supportive than her brother of women who sought scholarly or professional self-improvement, and she took pride in the accomplishments of her former boarders who became physicians and osteopaths, undertook graduate studies, or otherwise made careers for themselves. Olive mentions visiting lecturers, such as John (Captain Jack) Wallace Crawford. Other minor insights into life in Brockton include personal and public reactions to the assassination of McKinley and the San Francisco and Italian earthquakes of 1906 and 1908.
In both Eugene Marshall's papers and his sister's letters, there is a good deal of information about illness and the medical profession, in part because both brother and sister were both long-lived and survived many of their family members. Their father, Hayward Marshall, suffered a number of afflictions of age, most notably a circulation problem which nearly paralyzed his legs before his death in 1876. Marshall's eldest daughter, Fanny, developed a severe bone infection in 1882 which resisted treatment until her death in 1888; his wife, Lizzie, suffered a stroke in 1895 and died three months later. Olive's husband lived with a heart condition most of his adult life before succumbing in 1905 to a series of strokes. Olive herself died in 1917. These and lesser medical problems demonstrate, through the treatment and care prescribed, something of the level of medical knowledge current and the amount of confidence the medical profession inspired. Hayward Marshall sought help from a hypnotist and a clairvoyance doctor [letters, 1865-1868]. Fanny's illness was misdiagnosed from beginning to end by qualified doctors, while at least one quack approached Eugene with an offer for her quick cure. There is a little information on ordinary folk medicine, such as the application of leeches [diary, 1851]. Both Eugene and his sister would inform the other of diseases moving through the area. There may be some epidemiological interest in such reports of the following diseases: cholera, diphtheria, dysentery, erysipelas, influenza, measles, meningitis, scarlet fever, smallpox, typhoid, and yellow fever. Others would include infectious illnesses, such as tetanus, and ill-defined or veterinary diseases which are either cataloged under the bodily part affected or under the term used, such as hog cholera. Marshall also noted instances of alcohol and drug abuse, both in and out of the army.
There is also a notable amount of information, primarily in Olive's letters, on the medical education and career of her nephew, Marshall Lawrence Cushman, who took his undergraduate and medical schooling at the University of Michigan in 1901-1906, specializing in otolaryngology - ears, nose, and throat surgery - under the tutelage of Roy Bishop Canfield, then among the pioneers of such surgery in the United States. Lawrence Cushing went on to further study in Vienna and Berlin before starting a private practice in Lansing, Mich. Some additional biographical information on Cushing and Canfield may be found in the supplementary material folder filed with the first box of correspondence.
Eugene Marshall shared some of his sister's nativism, although his prejudices were mixed with more detached observation. Marshall commented on Germans and Irish in Texas and Minnesota [diary, letters, 1858-1883], Norwegians in Minnesota [diary, 1860], and Dutch generally [diary, 1852]. Some nativist comments relating to social attitudes in Wisconsin and political leniency in certifying naturalization there may also be found [letter, 1852].
In his later life, Marshall developed a considerable interest in his genealogy, most of which may be found in a special book compiled of family charts, etc. Marshall's record and scrapbooks as well as correspondence with family members, professional genealogists, and town clerks contain related information. He succeeded in tracing his ancestry back to the Mayflower and back to 1588. Among the 30 or more surnames mentioned in his research are the following: Cook, Wild, Hayward, Cary, Manly, Symmes, and Gannett.
As a farmer and the son of a farmer, Marshall's papers contain a good deal of information, observation, and detail concerning agriculture in Alabama, Dakota Territory, Iowa, Kentucky, Massachusetts, Minnesota, Tennessee, Texas, Vermont, and Wisconsin. Marshall's father kept Eugene informed of the prices of farm commodities in Massachusetts and Vermont where he maintained farms, and the elder Marshall offered some bits of folklore for determining the quality of dairy cattle when Eugene went into dairying briefly after the Civil War [letters, 1860-1875]. Eugene noted land prices in Minnesota and Wisconsin in the 1850s and in Iowa immediately after the wars. In shone same states he recorded aspects of frontier and pioneer life, including a vivid description of a fire in the grasslands of the Midwest [letter, 1855]. Other items related to agriculture in the Midwest of the 1850s include the role of farm women, the transportation of grain along the Mississippi, Marshall's speculation in patents for a machine which made fences from prairie sod, and the wages and hiring of agricultural labor. During his prewar trip to Texas, Marshall noted efforts made to improve the stock of the cattle industry and Texas agricultural laws which made land ownership by non-Texans difficult.
Marshall himself commented little on the labor movement, although he had some observations on labor and laborers, i.e., on attitudes toward work, working conditions, and wages, in particular contrasting situations in the North and South [diary, letters, 1904]. During his early years in the Midwest he recorded wages in the building trades while assessing the economics of life in the frontier towns. One of Marshall's later correspondents, Edmund Smalley of Chicago, intermingled commentary on low wages with speculation on the proper political strategy for the GOP; his letters contain a strong flavor of Social Darwinism [letters, 1910].
Marshall's geographic location and economic speculative interests brought him to note the progress and role of railroads. He personally invested in and followed the political future of railroads in Minnesota, particularly the Southern Minnesota and the Root River railroad companies [letters, diary, 1855-1862]. He used the progress and activity of the Galveston, Houston, and Henderson Railroad as a barometer of Texas' economic health during his trip there. Later, sister Oliver forwarded a newspaper clipping on the manipulation of the New York, New Haven, and Hartford Railroad by J. P. Morgan and its effect of New England [letter, 1910]. Related to the railroad industry are some 1859 diary observations on the controversial Rock Island Bridge (as a possible navigational hazard) and isolated citations of railway fares and telegraph rates in the 1880s and 1890s.
Other industries mentioned or described to some degree in the diary include the iron industry in the lower Cumberland, and Tennessee River valleys and some cotton mills in west central Tennessee [1862-1863].
A number of noteworthy incidents involving points of law and criminal justice appear in the collection: severe coporal punishments meted out to blacks in antebellum Texas, rough-and-tumble notions of pretrial custody in frontier Minnesota when the police sympathize with the prisoner's victim [diary, 1858], a wave of garroting and robbery in North Bridgewater, Mass. [letters, 1865], thievery of farm equipment in Vermont [letters, 1875], comments by a correspondent on the recall of judges and their decisions [letter, 1912], and the determination of insanity in a murder case in Minnesota [diary, 1864]. Marshall himself was involved in a long, drawn out settlement of his father's estate with Eugene's stepmother and her relatives in Vermont courts [letter, diary, 1876-1877; miscellany, 1839].
Marshall did not participate in organized religion. A Methodist revival held near his home in Minnesota in 1858 led him to express a dislike of displays of emotion in religion [letters, diary]. He expressed a similar dislike of the pageantry of Spanish-style Catholicism he witnessed in Texas [letters, diary], although he sent his eldest daughter to Catholic schools in the Midwest [letters, 1882-1883]. Marshall noted with amusement a stormy merger and renewed split of two Protestant congregations in Tennessee [letters, 1909].
Marshall was an active Freemason through much of his life and encouraged his brother-in-law to join the Masons [diary, letters, 1862-1863]. The assistance of Fred's lodge members to Olive during her husband's long illness is recounted in her letters [1897-1908]. Eugene Marshall noted with satisfaction the participation of army officers in the Independent Order of Good Templars during the winter camp at Sioux City, Iowa, in 1865-1866 [diary]. The Templars were modeled after the Freemasons as a fraternal-order but were basically a temperance society.
Occasionally Marshall discussed the observance of holidays - Thanksgiving in New England and on the frontier, Christmas in Texas, and the New Year of the new century in 1901.
The collection contains a few scattered items of pictorial interest: stationery portraits of Abraham Lincoln and Hannibal Hamlin, federal stationery of the Civil War, a letterhead picture of the falls of Minnehaha, and a post card of a ferry crossing at Ft. Snelling, Minn.
Scattered topics discussed include: Eugene's mild disgust that a relative took up spiritualism [letters, 1858], his account of the damage done by a flood in Tennessee in 1902, and a mention of lawn tennis in Tennessee in 1905.
Miscellaneous people who appear in the collection include: Warren Upham, secretary of the Minnesota Historical Society and a noted archeologist and geologist, who thanked Marshall for donating typescript and manuscript materials on Brackett's Battalion [letters, 1909-1910]; Solon J. Buck, then superintendent of the Minnesota Historical Society and later Archivist of the United States (1914-1948), who agreed to purchase a set of the Independent Marshall had offered for sale [letter, 1918]; and Robert Morris (1818-1888), the poet laureate of Freemasonry, who captained a supply steamboat in Tennessee during the Civil War [diary, 1862].
The Oversize Folder contains a certificate attesting to Marshall's membership in the Minnesota chapter of the Sons of the American Revolution.
The material reproduced on the microfilm reel consists of papers at the Minnesota Historical Society. There are four titles on the reel, all of which pertain to Marshall's military service. They are:
1) An Abstract of the history of Captain A. B. Brackett's 3rd Company - Minnesota Cavalry - organized at Fort Snelling Minnesota November 1st 1861
2) Narrative of the Civil War by Eugene Marshall
3) Report of the physical condition and natural products of that part of the Dakota Territory which was passed over by the Northwestern Indian Expedition commanded by Brevet Major General Alfred Sully during the summer of 1865. by Sigismund M. Rothhammer, and Remarks Upon Report of S. M. Rothhammer Acting Naturalist Northwestern Indian Expedition by Eugene Marshall, 1865
4) Battalion Order Book of A. B. Brackett
The Abstract covers the activities of the company of the title from its organization until it went into winter quarters at Ft. Ridgely, Minn., after the 1864 campaign of the Sioux Wars. The Abstract, a very terse outline of the unit history, was submitted by Lt. Mortimer Neeley, the last company commander, and was probably prepared by Marshall himself. Although the Abstract might serve as a reference tool for chronology and unit lineage matters, it is only 15 pages long and therefore can provide only a little detail of the-military actions it covers, such as the Tullahoma and Chattanooga campaigns and the Battle of Kildeer Mt.
The Narrative gives only a history of the formation of the Minnesota cavalry companies Marshall was associated with and the operations of the 5th Iowa Cavalry from the fall of 1861 to the end of 1862. Marshall presumably wrote and sent the Narrative to the Minnesota Historica1 Society in 1909, but his considerable use of the diaries he had kept during the war provided a greater feeling of immediacy than might be expected of a memoir of events 45 years past. The Narrative is 21 pages long, but it manages to include anecdotes and descriptions of insight and color concerning Gen. William T. Sherman, the appearance of Ft. Henry after its capture and occupation, and details concerning supply, the exchange of prisoners, and action at Ft. Donelson and Clarksville, Tenn.
The Report (24 pp.) was a survey of Dakota Territory, particularly of present North Dakota, by a hospital steward of German extraction temporarily acting as the naturalist for the Northwest Indian Expedition. The report covered the territory along the army's line of march in 1865; apparently a similar report had been filed for the area of operations in 1864. Rothhammer attempted to cover flora, fauna, geologic formations, climatic conditions, and the suitability of the area for agriculture. His report spent a considerable amount of time on the extensive deposits of lignite or low-grade, brown coal found in the area. In his remarks on the report (16 pp.), Marshall indicated that he had transcribed and edited the report and had eliminated material he thought inaccurate, overly florid, or not germane, particularly most of Rothhammer's commentary on the Plains Indians. Marshall also added a long section on a plateau region of present-day North Dakota which lies northeast of the Missouri River, which he called "the great Coteau of the Missouri," where many of the rivers of the Upper Plains found their headwaters. The remarks also disagreed with the report's evaluation of the region's agricultural potential and its explanations of various geological and hydrographic phenomena. Rothhammer's commentary, corrected by Marshall, appears to be among the first moderately thorough surveys of the Dakota area since that of Lewis and Clark.
The Order Book of Brackett's Battalion (88 pp.) begins with the order from Washington of Feb. 25, 1864, which separated the Minnesota cavalry companies from the 5th Iowa Cavalry and established them as an independent battalion. It ends with the expedition encamped back near Sioux City, Iowa, on Oct. 25, 1864. Orders include those pertinent to the battalion issued from other headquarters as well as those published by the battalion commander. Of special interest are the orders pertaining to the Battle of KiIdeer Mt. and those dealing with problems of military discipline. Most of the orders issued by Brackett's Battalion are countersigned by Marshall, who was battalion sergeant major and acting adjutant at the time.
Subject Headings
These are searchable subject entries for this collection. Performing a search on these subjects in the Duke University Libraries online catalog will bring up other related research materials.
Alabama -- History -- Civil War, 1861-1865; Emigration and immigration -- United States; Indians of North America -- Great Plains; Indians of North America -- Wars 1862-1865; Kentucky -- History -- Civil War, 1861-1865; Migration, Internal -- United States; Southern States -- Politics and government 1865-1950; Southern States -- Social conditions; Tennessee -- History -- Civil War, 1861-1865; Texas -- Politics and government 1846-1865; United States.--Army.--Cavalry -- History -- Civil War, 1861-1865; United States -- Description and travel; Voyages and travels; West (U.S.)--Description and travel; Donnelly, Ignatius, 1831-1901; Mann, Horace, 1796-1859; Sherman, William T. (William Tecumseh), 1820-1891
Contents of Collection
- Eugene Marshall Papers, 1839-1962, (35 boxes)
  - 1851 Sept 2 - Dec 4 (Box 1)
  - 1852 Aug 29 - Dec 31 (Box 2)
  - 1853 Jul 10 - Aug 13 - 14
  - 1853 Apr 1 - Dec 1 (Box 3)
  - 1856 Jul 8 - oct 14 (Box 4)
  - 1858 Aug 25, 26
  - 1859 Oct 31 - Dec 17
  - 1858 Jan 12 to 1859 June 1 (Box 5)
  - 1860 Apr 5 to 1861 Jan 31
  - 1859 Dec 17 - 18 to 1860 Jan 31 (Box 6)
  - 1861 Oct 19 - Dec 10 (Box 7)
  - 1861 Dec 11 to 1862 Feb 28 (Box 8)
  - 1862 Mar 1 - Mar 20 (Box 9)
  - 1862 Mar 21 - May 9 (Box 10)
  - 1862 May 17 - June 30 (Box 11)
  - 1862 Jul 1 - Aug 22 (Box 12)
  - 1862 Aug 23 - Aug 27 (Box 13)
  - 1862 Aug 29 - Oct 4 (Box 14)
  - 1862 Oct 4 to 1863 Feb 16 (Box 15)
  - 1863 Feb 5 - Mar 25 (Box 15)
  - 1863 Mar 26 - May 27 (Box 17)
  - May 28 to July 9, 1863 (Box 18)
  - 1863 Jul 10 - Sept 4 (Box 19)
  - 1863 Sept 5 - Oct 18 (Box 20)
  - 1863 Oct 19 to 1864 June 16 (Box 21)
  - 1863 Nov 21 (Box 21A)
  - 1864 Jan 24 - Feb 29 (Box 22)
  - 1864 Mar 8 - Mar 14
  - 1864 Mar 23 - Mar 24
  - 1864 May 4
  - 1864 Mar 18 - Apr 6 (Box 23)
  - 1864 Apr.7 - Apr 28 (Box 24)
  - 1864 May 2 - May 30 [typescript]
  - 1864 May 31 - Jul 4 (Box 25)
  - 1864 Aug 25 - Sept 7[itinerary] (Box 25A)
  - 1864 Jul 5 - Aug 18 (Box 26)
  - 1864 Jul 25 - Jul 31 (Box 27)
  - 1864 Aug 18 - Sept 22 (Box 28)
  - 1864 Sept 23 - Dec 31 (Box 29)
  - 1865 Feb 27 - Mav 28 (Box 30)
  - 1865 May 29 - Jul 20 (Box 31)
  - 1865 Jul 21 - Nov 30 (Box 32)
  - 1865 Dec 1 to 1866 Jan 24 (Box 33)
  - 1877 Sept 15 to 1888 June 11 (scattered entries) (Box 34)
  - 1894 Dec 30 to 1895 Oct 25 (Box 35)
  - 1905 Jul 10
  - Miscellaneous Oversize (Opaperfolder 1)